Next step is ע"ב. Ayin Bet. We actually are ahead a full
עמוד, amud, so we pick up on ע"ב עמוד ב' Ayin Bet
Amud Bet with the new משנה. Mishnah. Now the משנה Mishnah is
still somewhat in the theme of the father and the groom who
in partnership annul the vows, but it actually gets to a somewhat
in passing a very important central question which the גמרא Gemara is
going to open up and explore. And I should mention, if it
wasn't already obvious, that our פרק perek does what a lot of
the מסכתות masechtos do and a lot of פרקים perakim do, which
is start with the more obscure הלכה halakha which is maybe more
fascinating because it's all complicated, like what exactly is the nature of
the partnership between the father and the groom and who's the עיקר
ikar and who, the father's the עיקר, ikar, the groom is the
one that's piggybacking, how's it working in combination and so on, as
opposed to doing the normal thing, which would have been to explain
to you how הפרה hafarah takes place. Let's explain what the 24-hour
period is. Let's explain what הקמה hakama is. Let's explain
this. No, no, no. All of that gets sort of addressed along
the way. I mean, eventually we'll also address it more directly as
we start talking about the more obscure and in some ways more
interesting case if you already know all the other
stuff. So really just another proof that the גמרא Gemara and the
משניות Mishnayos were sort of organized for those already in the know,
not as
a נדרים Nedarim for dummies, right. So it's already for people who
are in the conversation and let's sort of talk about maybe some
of the more interesting cases first. Anyway, but this משנה Mishnah will
help us get to a central question. So let's take a look
at this משנה, Mishnah, the top of ע"ב עמוד ב'. Ayin Bet
Amud Bet. דרך תלמידי חכמים, Derech Talmidei Chachamim, it is the way
of תורה Torah sages, fascinating line in a משנה, Mishnah, דרך
תלמידי חכמים. Derech Talmidei Chachamim. I'm even trying to think when the
משנה Mishnah actually refers to תלמידי חכמים. Talmidei Chachamim. תלמידי חכמים Talmidei
Chachamim is obviously very common in the גמרא, Gemara, right, but like
when does a משנה Mishnah directly refer to this as a class
of
תלמידי חכמים? Talmidei Chachamim? Pretty easy enough to find out in one
minute on Bar-Ilan. דרך תלמידי חכמים, Derech Talmidei Chachamim, it is the
way of תלמידי חכמים, Talmidei Chachamim, עד שלא היתה בתו יוצאת מאצלו,
ad shelo hayeta bito yotzet mei'etzlo, before a man's daughter was going
to get married, and יוצאת yotzet here means נישואין, nisu'in, right? Remember
conceptually קידושין, kiddushin, אירוסין, eirusin, is she's still in her father's house.
Leaving the father's house means נישואין. nisu'in. So a man had his
daughter who was מקודשת, mekudeshet, before she was נישואין, nisu'in, he wanted
to make sure to take care of all of her נדרים, nedarim,
right? Because she made a vow prior to the נישואין. nisu'in. She
made a vow either before קידושין, kiddushin, after קידושין, kiddushin, but prior
to נישואין. nisu'in. What's going to happen once she becomes a נשואה?
nisuah? Can the father annul the vows at that point? No, he's
out of the picture. Can the groom, can the husband annul the
vows after she's a נשואה? nisuah? No, because it's קודמין, kodmin, right?
So the only opportunity to annul vows that preceded נישואין nisu'in is
to take care of it before נישואין. nisu'in. Okay? So here's his
daughter, she's מקודשת, mekudeshet, before the חופה, chuppah, he should take care
of any possible outstanding vows, okay? So דרך תלמידי חכמים, Derech Talmidei
Chachamim, עד שלא היתה בתו יוצאת מאצלו, ad shelo hayeta bito yotzet
mei'etzlo, before she would leave him, becoming a נשואה, nisuah, אומר לה,
omer lah, he would say to her, כל נדרים שנדרת בתוך ביתי
הרי הם מופרים. kol nedarim shenadart betoch beiti harei hem mufarim. Any
vows that you've taken in my house they're annulled. So give like
a blanket annulment, sort of like what we do at the התרת
נדרים hatarat nedarim on ערב ראש השנה. erev Rosh Hashanah. Okay, I
don't know what those vows are, you haven't told them to me.
Obviously she hasn't told them to him because if she told them
to him, the clock would have run out already, right? So it
sounds like he doesn't know what they are, but he just says
in case there are any vows that you have made that I
don't know about or whatever, I'm annulling them now while I still
have a chance. וכן הבעל, vechen haba'al, and so too the husband,
עד שלא תכנס לרשותו, ad shelo tikanes lirshuto, now you need the
groom to be part of this process, right? Because he also once
she's already מקודשת, mekudeshet, you need his annulment as well. So also
he wants to take care of it before the נישואין, nisu'in, right?
Because after the נישואין, nisu'in, if it's קודמין, kodmin, the father's out
of the picture and it is prior to him. The only reason
he can do it now is because it was still fundamentally the
father, but you need his participation. So the groom as well before
the נישואין, nisu'in, אומר לה, omer lah, will say, כל נדרים שנדרת
עד שלא תכנסי לרשותי הרי הם מופרים. kol nedarim shenadart ad shelo
tikanesi lirshuti harei hem mufarim. Any vows you might have taken before
the חופה, chuppah, הרי הם מופרים, harei hem mufarim, they are annulled.
שמשתכנס לרשותו, shemishetikanes lirshuto, once there's a חופה, chuppah, אינו יכול להפר,
eino yachol lehafer, he can no longer do it because they're קודמין.
kodmin. So basically we've got that this girl is once she's a
נשואה nisuah there's no chance of addressing earlier vows, so the father
and the groom together give her a blanket annulment. Obviously quite clearly
sounds like they haven't heard it, because then you wouldn't need it
to be framed in a blanket way, and because then it would
have had to say that
there's no clock that's running out here. There's no clock that's running
out. It sounds like they'll make sure to say it eventually, whatever,
it makes it clear that they have not heard it. Yes.
So I mean to me it seems like a pretty big חידוש
chiddush for a number of reasons because if I'm just thinking of
the פסוקים psukim in מסכתא דא masechta da ביום שמעו beyom sham'o
which sounds
like you know... Exactly. Sure.
Exactly. Exactly. So that's the question the גמרא Gemara asks, at least
as I said, this משנה Mishnah is just sort of telling us
something in passing, they better take care of it before she gets
to before she gets נשואה, nisuah, but it winds up telling us
something about the process of הפרה hafara and about this idea of
ביום שמעו. beyom shmo'o. So let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. בעי רמי בר חמא. Ba'ei Rami Bar Chama. So רמי בר
חמא Rami Bar Chama
asked. בעל מהו שיפר בלא שמיעה? Ba'al mahu sheyapir belo shemiah? Can
the husband, and it would be same about the father, we're not
going to distinguish, right? Can the husband or the father annul without
having heard? ושמע אישה דוקא הוא? Veshamah ishah davka hu? Does
the husband have to hear? Is that what's necessary to sort of
trigger his entire, give him the ability to do the annulment? או
לאו דוקא הוא? O lav davka hu? או לאו דוקא. O lav
davka. It's so funny to take a פסוק pasuk in the תורה
Torah and just say, yeah, לאו דוקא. lav davka. Okay. לא תעשו
כל מלאכה.
Lo
taasoo kol melacha.
לאו דוקא. Lav davka. So anyway,
so presumably what לאו דוקא lav davka here means is is not
that we're just completely saying the phrase doesn't mean anything, but the
phrase would mean, I believe, the following: he has 24 hours from
the time he heard. He doesn't have to hear to annul, but
once he's heard, he only has 24 hours to take care of
it. Not taking care of it within 24 hours of hearing
is interpreted as הקמה. hakama. That it makes sense, you heard about
it, you didn't object, right? So you're not objecting after hearing about
it for 24 hours, that is interpreted as הקמה. hakama. So it
wouldn't be לאו דוקא, lav davka, but it would be דוקא davka
in a particular way. You don't need ביום שמעו beyom shmo'o to
annul. The significance of ביום שמעו beyom shmo'o is that now you
only have 24 hours left. Okay, the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that,
but I think that that's what you have to say as פשט.
pshat. We're not just סתם stam saying לאו דוקא. lav davka.
Okay,
yes, wait, wait, yeah, go ahead. Wait, would it be, does
hearing mean without hearing,
like written notification?
Oh, that's an, if you say ביום שמעו beyom shmo'o is דוקא,
davka, then maybe you could talk about what would constitute. But the
גמרא Gemara isn't saying that because, as we pointed out, the משנה
Mishnah is clear he does it with completely unaware. Like there's no
clock running out, he says any vows you may have taken, right?
So it's clear that it's not just he didn't physically hear, but
he's unaware. Okay? So it's even a more of a לאו דוקא
lav davka than that. The לאו דוקא lav davka has to be
as I said, you don't need it to do the act of
annulment, but its relevance is that from the time you hear you
only have 24 hours left. Okay, so that's the question of the
גמרא. Gemara.
And the גמרא Gemara is not going to go to like, okay,
let's say someone can't hear?
It will go to that.
Yeah, maybe the way that the ושמע veshamah means that he has
to hear her make the neder, not that he hears later on
that she made a neder. He has to hear the neder come
out of her mouth. Is that what the גמרא Gemara says? לאו
דוקא.
Lav davka.
First of all, again, that doesn't fit the משנה, Mishnah, right? The
משנה's Mishnah case is that he says you came in after the
Mincha, but the משנה's Mishnah case is he says any vows you
may have made are annulled. So he didn't hear her do, he
doesn't know about it until her make it, and it still sounds
like he's annulling it. So it sounds like the פשט pshat is
he doesn't have to hear anything. Okay, anyway, so that's the question.
Does he have to hear at all or לאו דוקא? lav davka?
No, as I said, maybe it means that that's when he has
24 hours, but basically he doesn't have to hear in order to
annul.
תא שמע. Ta shema. Come from here. Our משנה. Mishnah. דרך תלמידי
חכמים עד שלא יצא בתו מאצלו. Derech talmidei chachamim ad shelo yatza
bito me'etzlo.
The way of Torah sages is that people who are, it's also
fun that it says תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim because maybe this is
just somebody who's like
conscientious about מדקדק בהלכה, medakdek b'halacha, right? Careful that his daughter shouldn't
have a vow that she's going to violate, etc. Maybe you have
to be a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham to know that you're able
to do this and that it's not a problem that you didn't
hear about it. I don't know, but it is funny the identifying
of this category as תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. Anyway, the משנה Mishnah
is דרך תלמידי חכמים עד שלא יצא בתו מאצלו Derech talmidei chachamim
ad shelo yatza bito me'etzlo before his daughter goes ahead and gets
has the חופה. chuppah. אמר לה כל נדרים שנדרת בתוך ביתי הרי
הן מופרים. Amar lah kol nedarim she'nadart betoch beiti harei hen mufarim.
Takes care of any possible existing vows. והוא לא שמע. Vehu lo
shama. But he didn't hear it. So how does this work? So
the גמרא Gemara says, נהי דכי שמע הוא דמפר. Nehi d'chi shama
hu d'mepar. No, no, no. He means he's going to annul it
when he hears. He says, I want to annul any vows you
might have made, okay, but they're not actually annulled now. What's basically
saying is that he sort of opens up the conversation with her.
He says, look, we gotta start, we gotta annul any vows you
might have made until now. So if there are any vows, I
want to annul them. And then hopefully she'll say, oh actually I
did take a vow and then he'll go ahead. Right. So it's
reading a lot into the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה's, Mishnah it's reading
it that he opens the conversation this way but he actually only
is going to annul it once he hears.
Does that mean that he actually you're saying he has to go
back and annul once he hears?
Right. Now what you're thinking is going to be wait one second,
it's going to come up. Maybe it should be חל לאחר זמן.
chal le'achar zman. We'll get to that.
Okay. אם כן כי לא שמע למה לי למימר? Im ken ki
lo shama lamah li l'meimar? So then why is he talking about
it now? If he hasn't heard it yet and you need him
to hear it in order to annul it. הא קמשמע לן אורחא
דצורבא מרבנן. Ha kamashma lan orcha d'tzurba merabanan. It's teaching you that
the way of a scholar is להדורי lehadurei to like... Go over
go back over it meaning to open up the conversation to engage
that possibility in order to get her to say something. Very, very
much not פשט pshat in the משנה, mishna, right? He says וכל
הנודרת על דעת v'chol hanoderet al daat as a way of getting
her to articulate what she may so that then he could annul
it. תא שמע מסיפא. ta shema miseifa. Finally, let's try the end.
וכן הבעל עד שלא תכנס לרשותו, v'chein habaal ad shelo tikanes l'rishuto,
but the husband before the חופה chuppah also says, אמר לה, amar
lah, the groom says אמר לה. amar lah. So you see he's
doing it before he heard. הגמרא hagemara says הכי נמי, hacha nami,
no here too, דאמר לה לכי שמענא, d'amar lah l'chi shamana, he
says to her when I hear. Now there's a question here what
the גירסא דגמרא girsa d'gemara is or how to read the גמרא.
gemara. Some have the גירסא דגמרא girsa d'gemara like we had before,
not לכי שמענא l'chi shamana but לכי שמא הוא דמפיס. l'chi shama
hu d'mefis. אם כן, im kein, blah blah blah, in the exact
same language as before. Which basically means he's opening the conversation to
get her to say it so that he can annul it. But
just our גירסא girsa which is just these two words: he says
when it takes effect, when he hears, without elaborating, when he hears
it he will annul it. But he says it before when he
hears means what I think Dov was
suspecting ראשונים rishonim interpret it the way Dov was suspecting which was:
right now I am saying to her I am annulling any נדרים
nedarim and this annulment will take place the moment I hear about
them. Okay, so which is a little funny, right, because you would
think that if you need to hear then you can't even do...
not only can the effect not take place now but the act
can't take place until the act of annulment can't take place. It's
sort of like this debate about דבר שלא בא לעולם. davar shelo
ba l'olam. One example of דבר שלא בא לעולם davar shelo ba
l'olam according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is a man says to
a woman הרי את מקודשת לי harei at mekudeshet li once you
get divorced from your husband.
Now that at least she's there, there's something holding her back or
whatever, she's not in a position to accept the קידושין, kiddushin, but
you could also say a non-Jew can say to a woman, okay,
הרי את מקודשת לי לכשאגייר. harei at mekudeshet li lich'she'agyir. Okay, now
you would think,
buddy, before you're even Jewish like we can't even talk about an
act of קידושין, kiddushin, like it's not just like some external problem
that can't take effect right now and it could be the effect
could take place later, like you can't even get the act off
the ground. Okay, but the גמרא gemara in order to deal with
the משנה mishna is coming into like a middle position. Maybe you
need to hear for it to take effect, okay, it'll only take
effect once the בעל baal has heard about it. But maybe he's
empowered maybe he's able to do the act and get the ball
rolling even before he's heard, it just can't take effect until he's
heard.
Okay that's an interesting middle position. We'll allow for the fact you
need to hear for it to take effect and we'll explain that
the משנה mishna is you did it now for it to take
effect later. Now the ר"ן Ran says so why didn't it say
that by the father, why did it only say that by the
husband? Right, good question. So here's the difference: for the father if
he winds up hearing later, the later might be after the חופה,
chuppah, right? That's what he's concerned about, it'll be too late it'll
be after the חופה. chuppah. So then she's completely out of his
control. And since she's completely out of his control at that moment
right it's hard to imagine that the act he did before he
heard when he wasn't able yet to annul can now combine with
the hearing at the time when she's totally out of his control.
Right, neither one of those is a situation where he could actually
like is in a position to annul and so how could that
actually work? By the husband it could be different. By the husband
he annuls now as an ארוס, arus, okay, so he has a
power to annul except he hasn't heard so that's preventing it from
taking effect. And he'll hear it once he's a בעל, baal, once
she's נשואה, nesua, when she's fully under his control and at least
for new נדרים nedarim it's true this annulment but at least for
new נדרים nedarim he's totally in a position to annul then, so
that maybe it's possible for it to
combine the act now with the effect later.
So the father gets around it by doing what again?
The father has to open up the conversation, hope she shares with
him and then annul. He doesn't get around it at all. The
גמרא gemara is reading the משנה mishna that if you have to
hear he basically has to get her into a conversation, get her
to share with him so that he can annul before she marries.
The groom is able to sort of say I'm annulling now which
will take effect when I hear and then even if he hears
after the נישואין nisuin it's okay because that's an acceptable time at
least as a husband for him to do an annulment.
So it could have been that either of them can
get her in a conversation?
No, no, but the father can say like when she's like, "All
right, any נדרים nedarim for the next nine and a half years."
Oh that's true, based on this read the father could say like
it'll take effect when I hear as long as when he hears
is while she's still under his in his בית, bayit, under his
control.
And the husband can say like from the moment he marries her
all right any
נדרים...
nedarim... any נדרים nedarim right once there's a נישואין nisuin he's basically
say right any נדרים nedarim that you make I'm annulling now and
it'll take effect the moment I hear about them. Of course he
would have to keep on saying that because that would only work
for נדרים nedarim that already existed, right? We're dealing with נדרים nedarim
that exist that you haven't heard about yet. A second... A second-level
question would be: Can you annul נדרים nedarim even before they exist?
Well, we haven't got there. Hold on, we're going to get there.
We haven't got there yet. Okay, so we've raised the possibility that
you can annul a vow that exists before you've heard about it.
That's certainly פשט pshat of the משנה mishna that it would actually
take effect. Okay, in order to accommodate though the משנה mishna we
said maybe not. Maybe the act of annulling can be and all
of this is that the vow already exists. The act of annulling
can take effect before you've heard about it but the effect of
it would only you know would only be once you've heard about
it. That's how we're trying to make the משנה mishna work with
the with the fact that you have to hear.
Right, because that's how we're interpreting it in the משנה.
mishna. Exactly. Let's so now we're going to keep on going. Okay.
Okay,
תא שמע. tashma. האומר לאשה. Ha'omer l'ishah. A man says to his
wife, this is a משנה mishna coming up. כל הנדרים שתדרי עד
שאבוא ממקום פלוני. Kol hanedarim she-tidderi ad she-avo mi-makom ploni. You know,
let's take a look at the משנה mishna because it's we'll see
it in the full. Turn two pages to ע"ה עמוד א'. ayin
heh amud aleph.
All right, so
האומר לאשתו. Ha'omer l'ishto. Guy says to his wife, כל
הנדרים שתדרי מכאן עד שאבוא ממקום פלוני. Kol hanedarim she-tidderi mikan ad
she-avo mi-makom ploni. Okay, I'm basically about to leave on a business
trip. Any vows that you make as of now until I return,
הרי הן קימים. harei hen kayamim. I'm מקיים mekayem them. לא אמר
כלום. Lo amar klum. That everybody agrees you cannot be מקיים mekayem
them. Now, these are vows that do not yet exist. Not only
has he not heard them, they don't exist yet. So you cannot
be מקיים mekayem a vow that does not exist. Okay, however, if
he says הרי הן מופרים, harei hen mufarim, I'm annulling them as
of now, these vows these vows that don't exist, so רבי אליעזר
אומר מופר, Rabbi Eliezer omer mufar, it works. וחכמים אומרים אינו מופר,
Vachachamim omrim eino mufar, it doesn't work. Now, why does רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer think you're more able to annul it before it exists
than to be מקיים mekayem it before it exists? So אמר רבי
אליעזר. amar Rabbi Eliezer.
Well, because if you annul it, it didn't exist yet anyway as
of now.
Exactly. אמר רבי אליעזר. amar Rabbi Eliezer. אם הפר נדרים שבאו לכלל
איסור, ראוי שיפר נדרים שלא באו לכלל איסור. Im hefer nedarim she-bau
l'chlal issur, ra'uy yafer nedarim she-lo bau l'chlal issur. He says a
נדר neder before it exists is in an even better position to
be annulled, right? Because you're annulling it, you're getting rid of it.
So if you can get rid of something once it's there, you
know, prevention is an ounce of prevention is worth a pound of
cure. Right? So if you can get rid of it once it's
already present, how much more so can you do הפרה hafara to
prevent it from from existing altogether? Okay, it's a preventative measure. And
that's why he says it's different than קיום. kiyum. קיום kiyum is
strengthening it. You cannot strengthen it, right, until it's there. It needs
to already have some strength to begin with for you to fully
anchor that strength. You can't strengthen it if it right when it
doesn't exist. But to prevent it or to get rid of it,
so why you're in a better position to prevent it from even
taking effect?
But one could say that הפרה hafara means it has to be
there already.
Well, okay. Anyway, אמרו לו, amru lo, they said back to him,
הרי הוא אומר, harei hu omer, no, the verse says אישה יקימנו
ואישה יפרנו, ishah yekimenu ve'ishah yeferennu, the husband will establish it and
the husband will annul it, את שבא לכלל הקם בא לכלל הפר.
et she-ba l'chlal hakeim ba l'chlal hafer. Only something that can be
established can be annulled. לא בא לכלל הקם לא בא לכלל הפר.
Lo ba l'chlal hakeim lo ba l'chlal hafer. If it cannot be
established because it doesn't exist yet, it can't be annulled. Now, it
might just be that that's how they understand the mechanism of annulment.
You know, it's just the mechanics work. Yes, conceptually, it's easier to
prevent something than to get rid of it. But the mechanics work
with something that's existent. Or it could just be like a גזירת
הכתוב gezeirat hakatuv and technically you're right, that should be the logic,
but the Torah says that they have to be in the same
פרשה. parsha.
You could also just say the opposite logic, right?
Anything that you could be מפר, mefeir, you could be מקים. meikim.
But רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer concedes that you can't be מקים meikim
it before it exists. That's that's his downfall, as it were, you
know? But okay. So here you have this fascinating debate. Forget if
you have heard about it. You have the possibility, right, that you
could be מפר mefeir it according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer before
it even exists. All right? So to be מקים meikim it has
to exist and maybe you have to hear about it as well,
etc. Okay, although no, like actually if you think about it according
to that משנה, mishna, you don't have to hear about it to
be... no, no, I'm sorry.
What? Right. You can't be מקים meikim it, right? The משנה mishna
says you can't be מקים meikim it if it doesn't exist yet,
right? Yeah, you can't be מקים meikim it if it doesn't exist.
Whether you need to hear about it is not clear. Anyway, so
the משנה mishna says that you can't be מקים meikim it if
it doesn't exist, but according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you can
be מפר mefeir it if it doesn't exist. So certainly you don't
have to hear about it according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So
let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: תא
שמע. tashma. האומר לאשה כל הנדרים שתדרי עד שאבוא ממקום פלוני, הרי
הן קימים, לא אמר כלום. Ha'omer l'ishah kol hanedarim she-tidderi ad she-avo
mi-makom ploni, harei hen kayamim, lo amar klum. You're trying to מקיים
mekayem something that doesn't exist, doesn't... you don't do anything because you
can only strengthen something once it's already there. It needs to already
have some strength to begin with for you to fully anchor that
strength. הרי הן מופרים, harei hen mufarim, but if you try to
be מפר mefeir before it exists, רבי אליעזר אומר מופר. Rabbi Eliezer
omer mufar. He says it does work and the חכמים Chachamim disagree.
Fine. They disagree just because it doesn't exist, but nobody says that
there's a problem that you didn't hear it. The whole debate is:
Can you be מפר mefeir before it exists? Nobody seems to be
bothered about the fact that you haven't heard about it. So the
גמרא Gemara says, והא לא שמע, v'ha lo shama, you didn't hear
it, and that doesn't seem to bother either רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
or the חכמים? Chachamim? So the גמרא Gemara says, הכא נמי דאמר
לכשאשמענה. hacha nami d'amar lich'she-eshamana. All right, so it'll be a case
where he says I am annulling it as of now that will...
take effect when I hear about it. Okay, so again we're doing
the breaking up of the process, the act of annulling, they're discussing
the act of annulling and that the act takes place before it
exists or not, but אהנא חינמי ona chinami the effect of it
will have to be will only take effect once he actually hears
about it. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, if that's true,
ולמה לי, v'lamah li, why does he have
to מהשתא, me'hashta, why does he have to then make the statement
before he goes on his trip? לכשישמעה ליה, l'chi shama leih, let
him wait till he gets back. In our משנה Mishnah we understand
why you have to do it now, because otherwise like it might
be like too late, right, it'll be קודם מן kodem min or
whatever, you need to do it before the נישואין. Nissuin. But here,
as long as it's not going to take effect till later, let
him just take care of it when it becomes an issue later.
So the גמרא Gemara says קסבר דלמא מטרידנא ההיא שעתא, kasavar dilma
matridna hi sha'ata, no, just coming back from my trip, I'll be
trying to get unpacked and take a nap or whatever and my
wife's going to tell me about some vow she took and I'm
not going to pay attention, by the time I wake up or
whatever, I'll have forgotten about it, it'll be 24 hours. Okay, so
that's why I want to take care of it now. Alright, so
basically again, פשט pshat clearly of our משנה, Mishnah, of that משנה
Mishnah is you don't have to hear about it, but now what
the גמרא Gemara is saying is we can sort of say that
you only it'll only take effect you might not have to hear
about it to do the act of הפרה, hafara, that we can't
get out of, but maybe it'll only take effect once he actually
hears about it. Okay, and we've also now introduced the position of
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says that you can actually do the
act of הפרה hafara
at least the act even before it exists. Alright.
Until she
makes the vow, he was
correct, that would be the נפקא מינה. nafka mina. Okay, תא שמע,
ta shema, come and hear. האומר לאפיטרופוס, Ha'omer l'epitropus, this is also
coming up or whatever, כל נדרים שנודרת אשתי מכאן ועד שאבא ממקום
פלוני. kol nedarim shenoderet ishti mikan ve'ad she'avo mimakom ploni. He's going
on a trip and he decides I'm not going to just do
it, I'm going to let some I'm going to let my friend
take over that. Okay, the guy who's sort of in charge of
running the house, I say to him, well we're going to see,
if you hear my wife take any vow, הפר, hafer, go and
annul it. והפר לה, vehefer lah, and he annulled it. יכול יהיו
מופר, yakhol yehu mufar, maybe they would be
annulled? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, אישה יקימנו ואישה יפרנו. ishah yekimenu ve'ishah
yeferenu. No, no, no, it's got to be only the husband can
do it, it's not a power that you can transfer. דברי רבי
יאשיה, Divrei Rabbi Yoshiya, that's what רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya says. אמר
לו רבי יונתן, Amar lo Rabbi Yonasan, רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonasan said
to him, מצינו בכל התורה כולה שלוחו של אדם כמותו. matzinu vechol
hatorah kullah shelucho shel adam kemoso. Everywhere why not? Why can't you
have a שליח shaliach here to do it? Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says here's an interesting debate about whether this is a power
that can be transferred, right? Normally you can make a שליח. shaliach.
There are some powers that can't be transferred. There are some things
the way like the רב חיים Rav Chaim and the בריסקרס Briskers
like conceptually sort of try to frame it, it's like there's some
things that are about you physically doing it, not about you being
empowered to do it. First of all, you can't make somebody a
שליח shaliach to do a מצווה. mitzvah. But also, let's talk about
even a legal act: חליצה. chalitza. You can't make somebody to be
a שליח shaliach to do חליצה, chalitza, right? חליצה chalitza is about
actually personally physically participating in the act. The way actually that that,
the איסור issur of חליצה chalitza is somehow is framed in this
למדנות, lamdanus, this בריסקרס Briskers approach, is that you're not the one
that is freeing your
wife, actually, she's not the one that's let's say freeing herself from
you, she's the one that's a little bit more active, right? It's
that the תורה Torah says if you go through the act, then
the תורה Torah sort of frees her. Okay, so it's not that
you now are empowered and you're the one, you do the act
and like the תורה Torah then releases or changes her status. So
anyway, it is important that even sometimes in legal acts it requires
the person, it's not seen as a power invested in the person
that can be transferred. Okay, so here this is the debate whether
the הפרה hafara is a power invested in the בעל ba'al that
can be transferred or not, or it has to be only the
husband. But now the גמרא Gemara says fine, ואפילו רבי יאשיה, va'afilu
Rabbi Yoshiya,
even רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya that says that it works,
excuse me, says it doesn't work, לא אמר אלא משום גזירת הכתוב
הוא, lo amar ela mishum gezeiras hakasuv hu, אישה יקימנו ואישה יפרנו,
ishah yekimenu ve'ishah yeferenu, that you cannot transfer this power. אבל דכולי
עלמא שלוחו של אדם כמותו. aval d'chulei alma shelucho shel adam kemoso.
Everybody would agree that if it weren't for that פסוק, pasuk, at
least in principle you could have transferred it to the שליח. shaliach.
Now why could you transfer it to the שליח? shaliach? והא לא
שמיע ליה. veha lo shimei leih. The שליח shaliach didn't hear the
vow. So how does the שליח shaliach have the power to do
it? It seems like the שליח shaliach is... no, excuse me, not
the שליח, shaliach, you didn't hear the vow, the שליח shaliach might
have heard it. You didn't hear the vow. So if you didn't...
right, the שליח shaliach is there, you're on your trip. You say
to your שליח, shaliach, if you hear her make a vow, annul
it. So he hears it, but you're not hearing it. So how
could your שליח shaliach do it if you didn't hear? Now the
obvious answer is I already gave it away, what's the obvious answer?
The שליח shaliach heard it. If if in if I can transfer
to him the power to annul, then why can't he also be
the person to hear for me? Okay, so here actually here, anyway
so the it's very interesting because
the
way the well read it inside but the way the ר"ן Ran
seems to sort of frame this is hearing is the circumstances under
which you then become empowered to annul, right? So I cannot trans...
I can... I can't transfer the power of annulling, but the act
of hearing is not that I somehow am empowered to hear, it's
just circumstances, the circumstances of me hearing empowers me to annul. So
I can't right, I can't make somebody my שליח shaliach, *shaliach* to
have experienced those circumstances. Once those circumstances exist, now I'm in a
position, now I can transfer that power I now have to the
שליח *shaliach*, okay? Another way of thinking about it, right, is that
hearing is a very passive type of an act. It's not you're
not you're not doing a legal act by hearing, right? So you're
not sort of the act that you do, the legal act is
the act of annulment. The hearing is the circumstances. So again, what
you can transfer to the שליח *shaliach* is a certain legal power,
but hearing is not that legal power. So therefore, the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* assumes that's quite fascinating, right? Let's read it inside the ר"ן
Ran *Ran* because it is fascinating that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't
even bother unpacking that.
So it says והלא שמע ליה *vehalo shama lei*, it's like six
lines from the bottom, end of the line in the ר"ן Ran
*Ran*, כלומר בעל ba'al *klomar ba'al*, the בעל ba'al, *ba'al* didn't hear.
אלמא לא בעי שמיעה shmiya *alma lo ba'ei shemi'ah*, you don't need
to hear. וכי תימא לעולם אימא לך דבעי שמיעה shmiya. ושאני הכא
דאיכא שמיעה דאפוטרופא *vechi teima le'olam eima lach deba'ei shemi'ah veshani hacha
de'ika shemi'ah de'apotropa*, the אפוטרופוס *apotropos* heard. ושמעון דשלוחו של אדם כמותו
*veshimon deshlucho shel adam kemoto*, and since he's like him, הוי כאילו
שמע בעל *havei ke'ilu shama ba'al*, it's like the husband heard. תרץ
בתוספות בשם רב יוסף ז"ל *teretz beTosafot beshem Rav Yosef zal*, דליתא
*delita*, that's not true. דאי סלקא דעתך דבעי שמיעה מיכא מידי דבעל
לא מצי מפר ושליח מצי משתי *de'i salka da'atach deba'ei shemi'ah mika
midei deba'al lo matzi mefer veshaliach matzi meshatei*, that if it needed
to be heard, so he basically makes it not exactly what I'm
saying, but like a little bit more of a technical point. If
the שליח *shaliach* heard and the husband didn't hear, then the husband
isn't in a position to annul, the only person in a position
to annul is the שליח *shaliach*, right? And
your שליח *shaliach* can't have power you can't have power that you
don't have, right? So therefore, that as that wouldn't work because even
though maybe the שליח *shaliach* did have the right circumstances, he can't
have the power if you don't have that power. Of course you
could say, well, you know, maybe I do have the power, if
he heard it, it's like I heard it, so now I also
have the power. Anyway, the simple explanation is, and I think that
actually it's in the תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*, it's my גמרא gemara *Gemara*
does not have a תוספות *Tosafot* in this פרק *perek*, but some
of the newer גמרות gemaras *Gemarot* actually have a תוספות *Tosafot* that
was added on the bottom from from a different manuscript. Yeah, let
me see, I think תוספות *Tosafot* there says a little bit more
simply along the lines that I was just saying about this issue.
Hold on, let me take a look.
Yeah, he says it in one line. ואי תימא שמיעת שליח כשמיעתו
ותרץ בקונטרס *ve'i teima shemi'at shaliach kishmi'ato veteretz beKuntres*, quoting רש"י Rashi
*Rashi*, דעניין שמיעה אינו נעשה שליח *de'inyan shemi'ah eino na'aseh shaliach*. Okay,
דעניין שמיעה אינו נעשה שליח *de'inyan shemi'ah eino na'aseh shaliach*. Doesn't explain
why, but I think it's what I said. Hearing is not a
legal act. You can't make somebody to hear for you. You can
transfer a legal power, you cannot make them you in order to
hear. Okay, so the גמרא gemara *Gemara* understands, it's a very nice
conceptual issues around שליח *shaliach*, but the גמרא gemara *Gemara* understands how
could you, so basically everybody agrees that if it wasn't for the
the idea of אישה ishah, יקימנו *isha yekimenu*, in principle you could
transfer this power to this שליח *shaliach*. But how could he be
empowered if he if you didn't hear? And the power to annul
only comes after you the husband personally have heard. So it seems
like you don't need to hear in order to have the power
to annul. Okay, so once again, another proof that you do not
need to hear. So the גמרא gemara. *Gemara* says, top of ע"ג
עמוד amud א' *Ayin Gimmel Amud Aleph*, הכא נמי דאמר לה לכשישמעינא
מפר לך *hacha nami de'amar lah lechish'shameina mefer lach*. So he says
to her, all right, he says I'm sorry, he says to the
שליח *shaliach*, when I hear about it, then you know, then you
should annul it. So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says what? לכשישמע לייפר
הוא *lechish'shama leifer hu*. When he hears about it let him annul
it. Why does he have to make a שליח *shaliach* do it?
No, סבר דילמא מטרדנא *savar dilma mitradna*, maybe again, maybe I'll be
distracted or whatever. So now of course it's still funny, like what's
the scenario? He comes home, he heard about it, he's distracted and
the other guy remembers to go ahead and annul it? So the
actual more simple explanation is, although it's does not necessarily fit so
simply in the words of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but is like
what was said before, that he's basically saying, you annul it when
you hear it, and it'll take effect when I when I hear.
Okay, so I can give you same way I could annul something,
remember, the only way the גמרא gemara. *Gemara* can accommodate all of
the evidence that sounds like you can annul before hearing is to
say you can do the act of annulling before hearing, but the
effect requires to have heard about it. So if that's true, I
can transfer that power to the שליח *shaliach*. You do the act
of annulling when you hear about it, it'll take effect when I
hear about it. Why don't you do it yourself when you hear
about it? I'll be distracted at that time. So you'll have already
set things in motion, you had annulled it when you heard about
it, and as soon as I hear about it then everything will
take care of itself. Okay, very similar to all the previous answers.
So again, all of the evidence is that you can annul before
you hear. The way the גמרא gemara accommodates all the evidence is
to say you've annulled now, you the שליח, whoever's annulled now, and
it takes effect, but at least we'll insist that it only take
effect once you hear. That we'll hold out for them. Maybe it
only take effect once you hear and you want to start the
things in motion earlier because you might be distracted at that later
time. Okay. So בעא רמי בר חמא. Bayei Rami Bar Chama. So
we don't have an answer to that. But now we're going to
raise a second level question which might implicitly address the first one.
בעא רמי בר חמא. Bayei Rami Bar Chama. So רמי בר חמא
Rami Bar Chama asks question number two.
חרש מהו שיפר לאשתו? cheresh mahu she-yafer l'ishto? Can a חרש cheresh
person annul for his wife? Assuming that you don't have to hear
in order to annul, because if you had to hear then it
would be a moot point. Again, assuming that hearing is literally hearing.
Okay. So assuming you don't have to hear, but you at least
have to be in a position where in theory you could hear,
a בר שמיעה. bar shmiya. Okay. Is it ודוקא? v'doka?
Yes. So it's a חרש שזה מדבר ואינו שומע. cheresh she-madaber ve-eino
shomeia. Right. So that, yes, correct. So אם תמצי לומר im timtzei
lomar בעל מפר בלא שמיעה, baal mefer belo shmiya, if you say
that husband can annul without hearing, משום דבר נשמע הוא, mishum de-bar
nishma hu, at least he's in the category of hearing. אבל חרש
דלאו בר נשמע הוא, aval cheresh de-lav bar nishma hu, a חרש
cheresh person that's not in the category of hearing, היינו דרבי זירא.
hainu de-Rabbi Zeira. Maybe he would be more excluded based on the
principle of רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. דאמר רבי זירא, de-amar Rabbi Zeira,
כל הראוי לבילה אין בילה מעכבת בו, kol ha-rauy l'villah ein billah
me-akevet bo, וכל שאין ראוי לבילה בילה מעכבת בו. ve-chol she-ein rauy
l'villah billah me-akevet bo. Anything that is fit to be mixed, you
don't actually have to mix it. But if it's not fit, then
the mixing prevents it from being good. This refers to a מנחה.
Mincha. If you bring a מנחה Mincha of sixty-one, I believe it
is, סאה, seah, sixty סאה seah with oil, then the תורה Torah
says you have to be בולל boleil the מנחה, Mincha, right? So
you have to mix the flour and the oil. But if you
didn't mix it, it's still good. Okay. Even if you just have
the flour and the oil separate. רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira comes along
and says that only if it is of a size that is
mixable. Once it's so large that it's not mixable, don't ask me
why a little extra makes it not mixable, I don't know, anyway,
once it's so large it's not considered to be mixable, then it's
no good. It has to at least have the ability to be
mixed even if it doesn't have to actually be mixed in practice.
Now of course, whenever this comes up, תוספות says, how do you
get to decide when it's enough to have the potential and when
you really need the thing itself? Like any תפילין tefillin that's fit
to be put on, I don't have to actually put them on?
When exactly do you say this? What exactly do you say that
is not clear? What tells חז"ל Chazal that in this מצוה mitzvah
the thing doesn't actually technically have to be done, it just has
to be in the category of being able to be done? So
I don't know the answer to that, but nevertheless the גמרא's gemara.
saying is if we're going to concede that you don't need to
hear and we're going to say ושמע אישה v'shama ishah is לאו
דוקא, lav davka, maybe at least what we'll leave ביום שמעו B'yom
shomo to be talking about, to be saying is, at least you
have to be in the potential, have to have the potential of
hearing. Okay. And maybe therefore a חרש cheresh would be no good.
That's the question. או דלמא o dilma ושמע אישה לא מעכב? v'shama
ishah lo me-akev? No, בדיעבד b'diavad you don't need ושמע אישה v'shama
ishah at all. We don't even just shrink it down to the
role of having the potential. You don't need it at all.
Something we're not considering though is maybe there's another way for her
to communicate.
Yes, correct. Right, we're assuming שמיעה means
שמיעה. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, תא שמע, ta shema,
we have a ברייתא. Beraita. ושמע אישה, v'shama ishah, the husband would
hear, פרט לאשת חרש. prat l'eishet cheresh. The ברייתא Beraita says to
exclude the wife of a חרש cheresh person. So it's very explicit
that that case is excluded. שמע מינה. shma mina. We now hear
that, again hearing is funny in this context, we hear that from
here. Now, the point is a lot of ראשונים Rishonim say, oh,
from this we can therefore implicitly assume that if a person is
hearing, they don't have to actually hear. Because since the ברייתא Beraita
only bothers to exclude the case of the חרש, cheresh, it sounds
like if just the fact that you didn't hear is itself not
enough to be a problem. It's only if you actually, it's only
if somebody's actually fully out of the category. And that's reinforced by
number one that this is a question that's built on the assumption
that you don't have to actually hear, and that all of the
previous evidence very clearly the פשט pshat of all that stuff that
we had on the previous עמוד is that you don't actually have
to hear to annul. So it's actually quite fascinating, right? The תורה
Torah says you hear and you annul, and according to at least
פשט pshat of everything and the way most ראשונים פסקן, Rishonim pasken,
you don't actually have to hear. Like I said, I don't think
it's so crazy because you could read the תורה Torah to say
from the time you hear you only have 24 hours or then
it's like you're מקיים mekayem it. But it's possible to annul without
hearing. All right. But what the גמרא gemara does say is if
the person's out of the category and a חרש, cheresh, then he
can't
annul. Okay.
So what you're saying is that's only for נדרים nedarim that were
already there, whereas for prophylactically?
Right, correct. That's the debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the
חכמים. Chachamim. Okay. One last question. איבעיא
להו. iba'ya lehu. They ask a question. בעל מהו שיפר לשתי נשיו
בבת אחת? baal mahu she-yafer l'shtei nashav b'vat achat? Okay. Can he
annul for his two wives together? He has two vows of two
of his wives on the same day and he says מופר לכם.
mufar lachem. Okay. So can he do that? Why? Because we say
אותה דוקא, otah davka, the same way we wanted to know about
ושמע אישה v'shama ishah was that
דוקא, davka, so it
says יפר אותה, yafer otah, הפר אותה. he-fer otah. Both at the
same time.
וכל אשר אסרה על נפשה יקום והניא אותה. ve-chol asher asrah al
nafshah yakum ve-henia osah. Yeah, you mentioned it
actually, it
says ואם ביום שמוע יניא
אותה,
ve-im beyom shomo
yania
osah, it says like one wife, it says in the
פסוק. pasuk. Uh-huh, two wives, אותה אותה. osah osah. What, I'm
sorry, yeah, hold on, hold on, let me see, let me see,
let me see, one אותה osah at a time. ואם ביום שמוע
יניא אותה. ve-im beyom shomo yania osah. ואם
הניא
אותה,
ve-im henia
osah, but if the father disallow her, right, not the vow, disallow
her. וכל אשר אסרה על נפשה יקום, ve-chol asher asra nafshah yakum,
ואם ביום שמוע אישה יניא אותה. ve-im beyom shomo isha yania osah.
But if her husband disallow her והפר את נדרה. ve-hefer es nidrah.
Okay, but the אותה osah by יני, yani, the הפר hefer is
on נדרה nidrah אשר אסרה נפשה, asher asra nafshah, right, it doesn't
say
יפר, yafer, does it say ואם הפר יפר אותם אישה
ביום שמעו? ve-im hefer yafer osam isha beyom shamo. So the הפרה
hafara goes on the נדר. neder. The יני, yani, which is to
disallow, goes on her. Right, because here it's in plural, ואם הפר
יפר אותם אישה ve-im hefer yafer osam isha ביום שמעו. beyom shamo?
So you can only have the plural going on the נדרים. nedarim.
כל נדריה וכל איסר אשר אסרה על נפשה, kol nedareha ve-chol issar
asher asra nafshah, right? So it sounds like that in the פסוקים,
pesukim, the act, the verb הפרה hafara goes on the נדר. neder.
You're voiding, you know, the vow. Whereas the יני אותה yania osah
means you're disallowing her. Okay, so anyway, so this is saying אותה,
osah, her, דווקא davka or לאו דווקא? lav davka? Or not? Or
maybe even if there are two wives. אמר רבינא תא שמע. amar
Ravina tashma. אין משקין שתי סוטות כאחת. ein mashkin shtei sotos ke-achas.
You cannot have two סוטות, sotos, you know, of one man has
two wives he's suspecting of adultery. Or maybe two men, but anyway,
either way, you can't do them both. But let's say that case,
you can't do them both at the same time. מפני שלבה גס
בחברתה mipnei she-libbah gas ba-chavertah because she sees her fellow wife there
that oh look, she doesn't have a problem with drinking and nothing
happened to her, nothing will happen to me. She doesn't realize that
her fellow wife is innocent and she's guilty or something. Okay, so
you don't want to, you want to, you know, you don't want
to interrogate people together. You want to have each process done separately.
רבי יהודה אומר לא מן השם הזה. Rabbi Yehuda omer lo min
hasheim hazeh. That's not the reason. אלא משום שנאמר והשקה אותה לבדה.
ela mishum shene-emar ve-hishkah osah levaddah. You should make her drink her
by herself. So here too it has to be by herself. Now
that's according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. What about according to the
חכמים? hachamim? Right? So there's some debate in the ראשונים, rishonim, maybe
there's a debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the חכמים hachamim
and we don't know the answer, but it's a debate. Others want
to say that maybe even the תנא קמא tanna kamma here agrees
that it's based on the פסוק, pasuk, but he's just explaining the
reason behind the פסוק. pasuk. Sort of like a רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon who's דורש טעמא דקרא. doresh ta'ama dikra. Okay, so it's not
exactly clear how the גמרא answers but it seems like the last
words in the גמרא is that it has to be individual for
the wife. Alright, should we end here? I guess we should end,
yeah. Do you want to? We could go. Do you want to
get
a
whole
דף daf ahead? Yeah, well let's get a דף daf ahead. Okay.
בוגרת ששהתה י"ב חודש. bogeres she-shahsah yod bet chodesh. We looked, we
saw this before. A בוגרת bogeres who is, and the way the
גמרא earlier read it is, or a woman who waited 12 months.
So again, this is a woman that was a מקודשת mekudeshes and
now the point is, it's not yet נישואין nisuin but it's the
time for נישואין. nisuin. Okay, it's been 12 months. Or now she's
a בוגרת bogeres and therefore it's assumed that you're going to have
the נישואין nisuin like very soon after she becomes a בוגרת. bogeres.
אלמנה, almanah,
or she's a widow, so she's outside of her father's house and
there was a קידושין kiddushin and it's a second marriage. So in
those cases of a second marriage, you only assume a month between
קידושין kiddushin and נישואין. nisuin. ל' יום, lamed yom, it's been 30
days. These are all different scenarios where it's the time for נישואין
nisuin but not נישואין nisuin yet. רבי אליעזר אומר הואיל ובעלה חייב
במזונותיה. Rabbi Eliezer omer ho'il u-ba'alah chayav bi-mezonoseha. Since חז"ל chazal said
that now is the time since you should have נישואין nisuin now,
you the husband are now obligated to start paying for her food.
So you're יפר, yafer, you're enough as if you're נישואין nisuin that
he can annul by himself. Good enough, but without the husband, without
the father. Of course it's very bizarre. If דאורייתא de-oraisa she's not
נשואה, nisuah, right, and this is all going to be לקולא, lekula,
how do they give him that power to annul? Okay. חכמים אין
הבעל מפר עד שתיכנס לרשותו. hachamim ein habaal mefer ad shetikanes li-reshuso.
No, you gotta wait til they're actually married for real. Let's take
a look at the גמרא. אמר רבה רבי אליעזר ומשנה ראשונה אמרו
דבר אחד. amar Rava Rabbi Eliezer u-mishnah rishonah amru davar echad. רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is saying that it's like they're really fully married
is saying the same as the משנה ראשונה. mishnah rishonah. דתנן, ditnan,
we taught in כתובות, Kesuvos, נותנין לבתולה י"ב חודש לפרנס עצמה. nosnin
li-vsulah yod bet chodesh le-farnes atzmah. You give a virgin 12 months.
twelve months, meaning for a first wedding, to arrange her trousseau. הגיע
שנים עשר חודש לפני נישואין. Higia shteim asar chodesh lifnei nisuin. The
twelve months have come and it's, they're not, he's not yet marrying
her. So, he now has his responsibilities kick in. אוכלת משלו, Ochelet
mishelo, he has to pay the food bills, ואוכלת בתרומה, ve'ochelet b'terumah,
not only financial responsibilities, she can even eat תרומה terumah if she's
a כהן, kohen, even though normally a person has to, a woman
has to be נשואה nesuah to a כהן kohen to eat תרומה,
terumah, she can eat תרומה terumah now. So you understand it's somewhat
analogous, right? Her ritual status also is already seen as a נשואה.
nesuah. So you have in the משנה, mishna, he can't annul, normally
he shouldn't be allowed to annul the vows unless she's a נשואה,
nesuah, but close enough, we'll let him annul, it's like she's a
נשואה. nesuah. She shouldn't be able to eat תרומה terumah unless she's
a נשואה, nesuah, but it's the time, so we'll consider it like
she's a נשואה, nesuah, we'll let her eat תרומה. terumah. Okay. אבל
היבם, Aval hayavam,
that's when it's a normal husband. But if it's the case about
that the husband died and we're waiting for the brother-in-law to do
יבום, yibum, then אינו מאכיל בתרומה, eino ma'achil b'terumah, then he is
not like the guy who's in the process of קידושין kiddushin and
נישואין, nisuin, and he's not in a position even if he's a
כהן kohen to have her eat תרומה terumah even after like the
twelve months. עשתה ששה חדשים בפני הבעל, Asta sheish chodeshim bifnei haba'al,
she was married to her husband for six months and then he
died. וששה חדשים בפני היבם, v'sheish chodeshim bifnei hayavam, and she waited,
I mean not married, there was קידושין kiddushin for six months. And
now she waited another six months for the יבם. yavam. או אפילו
כולן בפני הבעל חסר יום אחד, o afilu kulan bifnei haba'al chaser
yom echad, או כולן בפני היבם חסר יום אחד, o kulan bifnei
hayavam chaser yom echad,
the first case is the bigger חידוש. chiddush. Or she waited eleven
months and twenty-nine days, you know, for the נישואין nisuin and then
her husband dropped dead and now there's the brother-in-law. Or the reverse,
one day she waited after קידושין kiddushin with her husband and now
eleven months and twenty-nine days with the brother-in-law. In all those cases,
they don't combine. אינה אוכלת בתרומה. Eina ochelet b'terumah. She cannot eat
תרומה terumah by virtue of the fact that there's this brother-in-law waiting
to do יבום. yibum. Now, the פשט pshat of this משנה mishna
is that if actually her, she had been, got to that stage
of fit for נישואין nisuin with the, with her husband, it had
been twelve months, right, and קל וחומר kal v'chomer if she was
actually נשואה nesuah to her husband and then he died, that the
יבם yabam would then continue in that role and she would eat
תרומה terumah by virtue of the יבם. yabam. Right, but it seems
like פשט pshat of this is just that waiting for the husband
doesn't combine with waiting for the יבם. yabam. And there's a רש"י
actually says it's not true. That no matter how long she was
with her husband, the יבם yabam never—she never eats תרומה terumah by
virtue of the יבם. yabam. But רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam disagrees, he
learns this גמרא like the פשט. pshat. Okay, so basically what have
we said? Can a—when a woman is time for her to be
נשואה, nesuah, whatever the case might be with the brother-in-law and whether
that's the same or not, but when it's time for her to
be נשואה nesuah and it's been twelve months or whatever, she's considered
נשואה nesuah not only for financial purposes but even for איסור issur
purposes. She can even eat תרומה. terumah. So that's very similar to
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who says that the husband can do annulling
of vows. Okay, that's משנה ראשונה. Mishna Rishona. Okay, זו משנה ראשונה,
zo Mishna Rishona, that was the first teaching. בית
דין של אחריהם אמרו, Beit din shel achareihem amru, but a later
בית דין beit din said, אינה אשה אוכלת בתרומה עד שתיכנס לחופה.
eina isha ochelet b'terumah ad she-tikaneis l'chupa. No, we're not going to
give him that ability—her that ability—to eat תרומה, terumah, which is like
an איסור issur issue, until she's really a נשואה. nesuah. So this
seems like this question, how much are we prepared to consider her
to be a נשואה nesuah before she, you know, for איסור issur
purposes before she's actually a נשואה? nesuah? So that's a reasonable lining
up of the two positions. So the גמרא says, אמר ליה אביי,
amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye said to him, דילמא לא היא, dilma
lo hi, maybe it's not the same positions. עד כאן לא אשמעינן
משנה ראשונה אלא מיכל בתרומה דרבנן. Ad kan lo ashmi'unan Mishna Rishona
ela meichal b'terumah d'rabbanan. The משנה ראשונה Mishna Rishona only said she
could eat תרומה terumah which is a דרבנן d'rabbanan issue. אבל נדרים
דאורייתא אימא לא, Aval nedarim d'oraita eima lo, we'd never have allowed
the husband to annul the vows. Now, what do we mean that
תרומה terumah is a דרבנן d'rabbanan issue? Right?
Is תרומה terumah rabbinic?
So, it could be a position that like תרומה בזמן הזה דרבנן,
terumah bizman hazeh d'rabbanan, right, there's some גמרות that say based on
the question about קדושת ארץ ישראל, kedushat Eretz Yisrael, that all תרומה
בזמן הזה דרבנן, terumah bizman hazeh d'rabbanan, but that's not really פשט
pshat of this גמרא. This גמרא is making a different point which
is presumably based on another גמרא. Another גמרא says that מדאורייתא mi-d'oraita
even an ארוסה arusa can eat תרומה. terumah. The question is why
can the wife of a כהן kohen eat תרומה? terumah? So, there's
two possible פסוקים psukim to look at. One is, a, one is,
יליד, y'lid, what is it? Some...
אנשי ביתו הם יאכלו בלחמו, anshei beito hem yochlu b'lachmo, people of
his household, okay, and she's part of his household. The other is
talking about an עבד, eved, קניין כספו הוא יאכל בלחמו, kinyan kaspo
hu yochal b'lachmo, his, a thing that he purchased with his money.
So the question is, which case does the wife fall into? If
you say ביתו, beito, that means a נשואה. nesuah. If you say
קניין כספו, kinyan kaspo, קידושין, kiddushin, that's an ארוסה. arusa. So the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi actually says it's ביתו beito and even דאורייתא d'oraita she
needs to be a נשואה. nesuah. הבבלי The Bavli says it's קניין
כספו kinyan kaspo and דאורייתא d'oraita an ארוסה arusa can eat תרומה.
terumah. So why did they say she had to be a נשואה?
nesuah? You tell me. Here's this woman, not you, well. You
here's this woman, she's betrothed, she's an ארוסה, arusa, דאורייתא de-oraita she
can eat תרומה. terumah. What's the possible reason the rabbis wouldn't want
her to be eating תרומה terumah right now? Can you think? She's
a non-כהן, kohen, she's not from a
כהן kohen family. Her כהן kohen groom is feeding her תרומה. terumah.
What's she doing? She is going to be sharing this with her
family, which are not כהנים, kohanim, because she's still living in her
father's house, right? So that's the most simple reason. There's another reason
also, which is maybe between now and the נישואין, nissuin, he'll discover
something about her he didn't like and it'll be a מקח טעות,
mekach ta'os, and then retroactively she never would have been married. Okay.
But the more simple reason is just she shouldn't go ahead and
share it with members of her household. So the only reason she
can't eat is rabbinic. So it's not a big deal to say
once it's the time of נישואין, nissuin, we'll treat you like a
נשואה, nesuah, right, and then and then we'll and then you will
be allowed to eat. The ר"ן Ran even goes further. He says
because if you think about it, right, at this stage
where he is paying now for her food bill, well how would
that work? I don't know, even if he's paying for her bill
but she could still share it. Anyway, but the point is that
right now it's all rabbinic. So since it's all rabbinic, it's not
so it wouldn't be so terrible to say you deserve to be
a נשואה nesuah now, we're going to let you eat. מה שאין
כן נדרים. mash'en kein nedarim. How could נדרים, nedarim, if she's not
really a נשואה, nesuah, how could the husband annul the vows? So
even according to the משנה ראשונה Mishna Rishona that was only rabbinic.
That wouldn't explain how he could annul the vows. Okay, now it's
really raising the question, what is the position of רבי אליעזר? Rabbi
Eliezer? How could רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say he annuls the vows?
So let's read the last line. ועד כאן לא שמעת ליה לרבי
אליעזר אלא לגבי נדרים. ve-ad kan lo shama'as leh le-Rabbi Eliezer ella
legabei nedarim. And even רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, maybe he would even
say that she can't eat תרומה. terumah. And even though she can't
eat תרומה, terumah, the husband could still annul the vows. Why should
vows be better?
Because by נדרים, nedarim, כדרב פנחס משמיה דרבא, kide-Rav Pinchas mishmei de-Rava,
because that would follow the position of רב פנחס משמיה דרבא. Rav
Pinchas mishmei de-Rava. דאמר כל הנודרת על דעת בעלה היא נודרת. de-amar
kol ha-noderes al da'as ba'alah hi noderes. That if a woman takes
a vow and she's already in this relationship with her husband, that
she is like that she's already a נשואה, nesuah, right, so therefore
she basically means I'm only vowing assuming that he's going to be
okay with it. All right.
And that's in her mind that it's בתנאי bitnai that he's okay
with it. All right. And that's why it works, but not that
she really is halachically considered a נשואה. nesuah. It's circumstances that affect
her psychological state. אבל תרומה אפילו מדרבנן נמי לא אכלה בה. aval
terumah afilu midrabanan nami lo achla bah. But by תרומה, terumah, maybe
from a formal perspective he's saying I don't consider her a נשואה.
nesuah. I'm not going to let her eat תרומה. terumah. But what
I will say is because of the relationship now she's got with
her husband and she's already been twelve months and it's time to
get married and he's providing for her whatever, she's now thinking about
being married to this guy and she has him in mind when
it comes to the issue it's like an implicit תנאי tnai when
it comes to the issue of a vow, but not before twelve
months, then it's a distant thing, it's not like she sees herself
in that relationship. Now that is a pretty weak answer because technically
because then like yeah, I mean, it basically means that what he
he's not The ר"ן Ran asks the following question. The ר"ן Ran,
says so if I say I am taking a vow על דעת
al da'as Dov there or Seth let's say so we don't get
confused with Dovs there, so does that mean that Seth can now
say I like am מיפר meifer it? I don't want it, but
I don't explicitly say על תנאי al tnai that Seth is okay.
I just say like על דעת al da'as Dov, I'm thinking about
or Seth excuse me while I'm making this vow. Does that mean
he can annul it? Or let's ask another question. If it's על
דעת בעלה היא נודרת, al da'as ba'alah hi noderes, can the husband
now be מיפר meifer more than twenty-four hours later? Right? Does so
I mean do the mechanics play in?
So the ר"ן has a very interesting answer to this. Take a
look at the ר"ן, he says like
this. He says ואיכא דילפי מהכא, ve-ika de-yalfei me-hacha, some learn from
here.
דמי שנודר על דעת חבירו הרי זה יכול להתיר נדרו שלא על
פי חכם. de-mi she-noder al da'as chaveiro harei ze yachol lehatir nedar
shelo al pi chacham. דכי היכי דאמרינן הכא דמשום הכי מצי בעל
לחודיה להפיר משום דנדרה על דעתיה, de-chei heichi d'amrinan hacha demishum hachi
mati ba'al lachudei lehafer mishum de-nadra al da'ateh, דמפרש נמי על דעת
חבירו מצי מיפר. de-mefaresh nami al da'as chaveiro mati meifer. דלא גרע
ממפרש שחבירו, de-lo gar me-mefaresh she-chaveiro, if you explicitly say it's על
דעת חבירו, al da'as chaveiro, מסתמא דבעל mistama de-ba'al then implicitly on
the דעת da'as of the husband. דהיינו טעמא הכא, de-hainu ta'ama hacha,
assuming we פסקן pasken like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, which is funny
because actually the חכמים chachamim reject רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, and they
say the husband can't the guy can't be מיפר, meifer, but at
least within רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. דהתם משום דכנדר על תנאי דמי.
de-hasam mishum de-keneder al tnai dami.
Okay, so that's what some say. That at least within רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, if you say I'm doing it על דעת al da'as
somebody else, then they're like the husband and they can annul. Okay,
וזו אצלי שגגת הוראה. ve-zo etzli shegagah hura'ah.
This is like a real error in פסק. psak. דאף על גב
דאמר דעל דעת בעלה היא נודרת, de-af al gav de-amar d'al da'as
ba'alah hi noderes, אפילו הכי צריך שהבעל שיפר לה באותו לשון שכתב
לו תורה. afilu hachi tzarich she-ha-ba'al she-yafer lah be-oso lashon she-katav lo
Torah. Right, you
have to do a formal act of הפרה, hafara, you can't just
say oh well I don't like it I don't agree. וגזירת הכתוב
הוא u-gzeirat hakatuv hu ומשום הכי אין כל לשונות שוים בו. u-mishum
hachi ein kol leshonot shavim bo. You need the right type of
language. We're going to get to this. We raised this question before:
is there a formal act, what's language? וכדאמרינן לקמן. u-ched'amrinan lekaman. ואי
אמרת דבנודר על דעת חבירו נמי איכא מאן דמפר משום דכנדר על
תנאי דמי, v'ei amrat d'be-noder al da'at chaveiro nami ika man d'meifer
mishum d'ke-neder al t'nai dami, הרי הפרתו של בעל ואחר ראויה שתהא
נאמרת בכל לשון, harei hafarato shel ba'al ve-acher r'uya she-t'hei nemeret be-chol
lashon,
then you why would you have to do a formal לשון של
הפרה? lashon shel hafarah? And I would say the question I would
say also like if like, you know, what, presumably he has only
twenty-four hours, right? It's presumably follows the same patterns of הפרה, hafarah,
it's not like you can do it at any time. אלא ודאי
רב פנחס הכי קאמר, ela vadai Rav Pinchas hachi ka-amar, נהי דהפרה
דבעל גזירת הכתוב הוא, nihi d'hafarah d'ba'al gzeirat hakatuv hu, it's a
גזירת הכתוב gzeirat hakatuv that
the Torah empowered him and it has formal rules. ומיהו משום הכי
זכתה תורה לבעל בהפרת נדריה. u-mihu mishum hachi zachata Torah la-ba'al be-hafarat
nedareha.
Here's the reason it's a formal mechanism. It's not just a תנאי
t'nai or whatever. The הפרה hafarah is a formal mechanism, got twenty-four
hours, formal language, etc. But here's the person why is it the
בעל that's the one empowered with this ability? משום דעל דעת בעל
היא נודרת, mishum d'al da'at ba'al hi noderet, because it's like a
real amazing דרשינן טעמא דקרא. darshinan ta'ama d'kra. Why did the Torah
invest the husband? So you know, actually this is not what I
would have said in פשט pshat at all. It's very empowering to
the woman. I mean, whatever, switches it. It's not invest the husband
because hey, פשיטא, p'shita, you're in my house and therefore what I
get to say goes, right? That's I think how normally you would
understand like why, you know, he's the guy in control, you can't
do anything against his will. No, it's reversing it. The reason the
Torah empowers the husband is the presumption that the wife would only
do it if the husband would agree. But it makes it about
her דעת. da'at. הילכך, hilkach, that's how we're interpreting what's going on
in the פסוק, pasuk, why the husband is invested. הילכך, hilkach, with
that power. כל שהיא נודרת על דעתו, kol she-hi noderet al da'ato,
if anybody would sit that role, now presumably not a stranger, it
would have to be somebody that's in a pseudo-husband or an ארוס
arus type of a position. חלה עליו גזירת הכתוב דאמר רחמנא. chala
alav gzeirat hakatuv d'amar Rachmana.
So we're expanding, what we're doing is we're actually דרשינן טעמא דקרא
darshinan ta'ama d'kra and we're saying when the Torah says husband, בעל,
you know, אישה, husband includes even an ארוס arus after twelve months
when he is, when the relationship is effectively the same and her
דעת da'at is effectively the same as it would be after נישואין.
nisuin. So it's a way that we redefine what are the parameters,
right, of that category of husband in the Torah. אבל הנודר על
דעת חבירו דלא כתיב ביה רחמנא מידי, aval ha-noder al da'at chaveiro
d'lo ketiv bei Rachmana midi, but if it's a guy that wasn't
the husband at all, some סתם stam stranger, okay, ודאי לא מצי
מפר. vadai lo matzi meifer. Okay. והשתא, v'hashta, and of course if
you explicitly make a תנאי, t'nai, you can explicitly make whatever תנאי
t'nai you want. But this concept of על דעת, al da'at, it's
a beautiful read of the Ran, I mean, you know, it's really,
you know, we're going to go ahead and the Torah says husband
and Rabbi Eliezer says yeah, but husband doesn't have to be full
נישואין. nisuin. It could be an ארוס arus who's in the position
as the relationship has gotten to the stage where it's the similar
dynamic as with a husband. And that's also in the Torah's category
of husband, right? It's very fascinating read of it, but you know,
you חזל Chazal in a way do this all the
time. But it's really like, okay, forget, you know, it's not a
complete rejection of the formalisms. Anybody that, oh well, I care for
my sister as much of my husband and I would only want
it to be no no no, it has to be somebody we
can fit into the husband category. This guy is an ארוס. arus.
He could, right, it's just that he's not yet נישואין, nisuin, but
it's close enough that we can say it's like it's נישואין nisuin
and the Torah would consider it to be a case of נישואין
nisuin by this stage already because of the reasons that are relevant
about this case. Okay, and that explains at least Rabbi Eliezer's position
of why it can. Again, the חכמים Chachamim disagree, but that at
least explains Rabbi Eliezer. Okay, שם? sham?
Yeah, they're not living together yet.